<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:base="https://mert.biricik.de/">
  <title>Mert Biricik's Blog Feed</title>
  <subtitle>The latest posts from Mert Biricik's personal blog on full stack development, data science, and cybersecurity.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://mert.biricik.de//rss.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://mert.biricik.de//"/>
  <updated>2025-08-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://mert.biricik.de//</id>
  <author>
    <name>Mert Biricik</name>
    <email>mert@biricik.de</email>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Hello World!</title>
    <link href="https://mert.biricik.de/blog/hello_world/"/>
    <updated>2025-08-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://mert.biricik.de/blog/hello_world/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Welcome to my new blog!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the first post, demonstrating how easy it is to add content using Markdown files with Eleventy. I&#39;m excited to share my thoughts on full-stack development, data science, and cybersecurity here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am planning to update here at least bi-weekly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;What&#39;s Next?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;More technical deep-dives&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Project showcases&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thoughts on industry trends&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Mert Biricik</name>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Demystifying Cybersecurity: A Deep Dive into CompTIA Security+ Fundamentals</title>
    <link href="https://mert.biricik.de/blog/comptia-security-plus-fundamentals/"/>
    <updated>2025-08-10T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://mert.biricik.de/blog/comptia-security-plus-fundamentals/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;Demystifying Cybersecurity: A Deep Dive into CompTIA Security+ Fundamentals&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cybersecurity is a dynamic and critical field, constantly evolving to combat new threats. For anyone looking to establish a strong foundation in this domain, the CompTIA Security+ certification is an excellent starting point. This post will break down key concepts from the Security+ curriculum, covering essential controls, core security principles, threat actors, common vulnerabilities, and more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s dive in!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.1 Understanding Cybersecurity Controls&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cybersecurity controls are safeguards or countermeasures to avoid, detect, counteract, or minimize security risks to physical property, information, or any other asset. They can be categorized in several ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Technical Controls:&lt;/strong&gt; These are implemented using systems and technology. Examples include operating system controls, firewalls that filter network traffic, and antivirus software designed to detect and remove malicious programs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managerial Controls (Administrative Controls):&lt;/strong&gt; These are policies and procedures established by management to govern security. This includes creating clear security policies and defining standard operating procedures (SOPs) that employees must follow.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Operational Controls:&lt;/strong&gt; These controls are implemented by people and focus on the day-to-day security activities. Examples include the presence of security guards, regular security awareness training programs for employees, and incident response procedures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Physical Controls:&lt;/strong&gt; These controls limit physical access to facilities and assets. This can involve guard shacks at entry points, fences, locks on doors, and badge readers to control entry to restricted areas.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Control Types: How Controls Function&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond their category, controls also have different functions in how they mitigate risk:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Preventive:&lt;/strong&gt; These controls aim to stop an incident from happening in the first place. Think of a strong firewall preventing unauthorized access – it&#39;s the &amp;quot;you shall not pass&amp;quot; of cybersecurity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deterrent:&lt;/strong&gt; Designed to discourage an intrusion attempt. The threat of consequences, like demotion for policy violations, or visible warning signs (e.g., &amp;quot;CCTV in operation&amp;quot;), serve as deterrents.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Detective:&lt;/strong&gt; These controls identify and log an attempt or an ongoing incident. Intrusion detection systems (IDS) or security logs are prime examples, alerting you to suspicious activity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Corrective:&lt;/strong&gt; Applied after an event has occurred to minimize damage or restore systems. The goal is minimal downtime, such as restoring data from backups after a ransomware attack.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compensating:&lt;/strong&gt; Used when a primary control cannot be implemented or is impractical. It&#39;s a control that achieves the same security objective through alternative means.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Directive:&lt;/strong&gt; These controls guide a subject towards security compliance. While often considered &amp;quot;weak&amp;quot; on their own, they direct users to follow security best practices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.2 The CIA Triad: The Pillars of Information Security&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The CIA Triad (sometimes called the AIC Triad) represents the three fundamental principles of information security:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://mert.biricik.de/blog/comptia-security-plus-fundamentals/:/ad8fb157c2696d2ca3892b1aadc16cc7.png&quot; alt=&quot;CIA Triad Diagram&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Confidentiality:&lt;/strong&gt; Ensuring that information is accessible only to those authorized to have access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Access Controls:&lt;/strong&gt; Restricting who can view or modify data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Encryption:&lt;/strong&gt; Transforming data into a coded format to prevent unauthorized reading.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integrity:&lt;/strong&gt; Maintaining the accuracy and completeness of data, ensuring it has not been altered or destroyed in an unauthorized manner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hashing:&lt;/strong&gt; Creating a unique, fixed-size digital fingerprint of data. If the data changes, the hash changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Digital Signatures:&lt;/strong&gt; When a hash is encrypted with a private key, it becomes a digital signature, providing both integrity and authenticity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Certificates:&lt;/strong&gt; Digital documents that bind a public key to an identity, used to verify integrity and authenticity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Non-Repudiation:&lt;/strong&gt; The inability to deny having performed an action or made a statement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Availability:&lt;/strong&gt; Ensuring that authorized users have timely and uninterrupted access to information and resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Redundancy:&lt;/strong&gt; Duplicating critical components or systems to ensure continued operation if one fails.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fault Tolerance:&lt;/strong&gt; The ability of a system to continue operating without interruption when one or more of its components fail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patching:&lt;/strong&gt; Applying updates to software to fix bugs and security vulnerabilities, ensuring system stability and availability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.2.1 Non-Repudiation: Proving What Was Said&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Non-repudiation means you cannot deny what you have said or done. It provides undeniable proof of origin and integrity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proof of Integrity:&lt;/strong&gt; Verifies that data has not been changed since it was created or sent. Data remains accurate and consistent. Hashes are crucial here, acting as a data fingerprint. However, a hash only validates the data&#39;s integrity, not its origin.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proof of Origin:&lt;/strong&gt; Proves the source of a message or data. This is achieved through authentication mechanisms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To ensure a signature is not fake (non-repudiation), digital signatures are used. A digital signature is essentially the encrypted hash of a message using a private key, which can then be decrypted with the corresponding public key to verify authenticity and integrity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.2.2 AAA Framework: Identity and Access Management&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AAA framework is a cornerstone of identity and access management:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Identification:&lt;/strong&gt; The process by which a user claims an identity (e.g., by providing a username).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authentication:&lt;/strong&gt; The process of verifying that the claimed identity is genuine (e.g., by providing a password, biometric, or token). Certificate Authorities (CAs) play a role in issuing and managing digital certificates used for authentication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authorization:&lt;/strong&gt; Determining what an authenticated user is permitted to do or access. Abstraction (like using groups) is often used to streamline administration of permissions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accounting:&lt;/strong&gt; Tracking user activities, including what resources they accessed, when, and for how long. This provides an audit trail.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.2.3 Gap Analysis: Finding the Gaps in Security&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://mert.biricik.de/blog/comptia-security-plus-fundamentals/:/8cbb34c5f4a3cc0a43c60f3b15b8998c.png&quot; alt=&quot;Gap Analysis Diagram&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gap analysis is a process used to compare the current state of an organization&#39;s security posture against a desired state or a recognized standard (like ISO/IEC 27001). It involves:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Evaluating People and Processes:&lt;/strong&gt; Assessing the human and procedural elements of security.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comparing Weaknesses and Solutions:&lt;/strong&gt; Identifying security weaknesses and proposing solutions to compensate for them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analysis and Report:&lt;/strong&gt; The outcome is a detailed analysis and report outlining the identified gaps and recommendations for improvement.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.2.4 Zero Trust: Never Trust, Always Verify&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zero Trust is a security model based on the principle of &amp;quot;never trust, always verify.&amp;quot; It assumes that no user or device, whether inside or outside the network perimeter, should be trusted by default.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Different Functional Planes of Network:&lt;/strong&gt; Zero Trust often conceptualizes networks in terms of a data plane (where data flows) and a control plane (where policies are enforced).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adaptive Identity:&lt;/strong&gt; Identity verification is continuous and adaptive, considering context like device health, location, and behavior.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Threat Scope Reduction:&lt;/strong&gt; By segmenting networks and enforcing granular access, the potential scope of a breach is significantly reduced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Policy-Driven Access Control:&lt;/strong&gt; Access decisions are strictly based on policies, not network location.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Security Zones:&lt;/strong&gt; Networks are divided into micro-segments or security zones.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Policy Enforcement Point (PEP):&lt;/strong&gt; The point where access policies are enforced, often at the individual resource level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.2.5 Physical Security: Protecting the Perimeter&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Physical security measures are crucial for protecting physical assets and limiting unauthorized access to facilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Access Control Vestibules (Man Traps):&lt;/strong&gt; Small rooms with two doors, where the first must close before the second opens, trapping an unauthorized individual.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CCTV (Closed-Circuit Television):&lt;/strong&gt; Surveillance cameras for monitoring and recording activity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Security Guards:&lt;/strong&gt; Human presence for monitoring, patrolling, and responding to incidents.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sensors:&lt;/strong&gt; Various types of sensors (e.g., motion, door/window, vibration) to detect intrusions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Infrared Cameras:&lt;/strong&gt; Used for night vision and detecting heat signatures.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.2.7 Deception and Disruption: Trapping Attackers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These techniques are used to mislead or disrupt attackers, gathering intelligence on their methods.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Honeypot:&lt;/strong&gt; A decoy system designed to attract and trap attackers, making them believe it&#39;s a legitimate target. It&#39;s often assumed the attacker is a machine (automated attack).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Honeynet:&lt;/strong&gt; A network of honeypots, providing a more realistic and complex target for attackers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Honey Files:&lt;/strong&gt; Decoy files placed on systems to detect unauthorized access.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Virtual Bear Trap:&lt;/strong&gt; A metaphorical term for a honeypot, designed to ensnare attackers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Honeytoken:&lt;/strong&gt; A fake credential (e.g., API key, database entry) placed in a system to detect when it&#39;s accessed by an unauthorized party.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.3 Change Management: Controlling the Flow of Change&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Change management is a formal process for managing any alteration to an IT system or environment. Its goal is to avoid downtime, confusion, and mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Formal Process:&lt;/strong&gt; Any change needs to follow a defined, formal process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rollback Procedures:&lt;/strong&gt; Plans for reverting a change if it causes unforeseen problems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Clear Policies:&lt;/strong&gt; Well-documented guidelines for how changes are initiated, approved, and implemented.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Change Request Form:&lt;/strong&gt; A standardized form to document the details of a proposed change, including:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Purpose:&lt;/strong&gt; Why the change is needed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scope:&lt;/strong&gt; What systems or areas will be affected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Schedule:&lt;/strong&gt; When the change will occur.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Systems and Impact:&lt;/strong&gt; Detailed analysis of affected systems and potential consequences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risk Associated with the Change:&lt;/strong&gt; Identification and assessment of potential risks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Approval:&lt;/strong&gt; Changes require formal approval from relevant stakeholders.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;End-User Acceptance:&lt;/strong&gt; Ensuring that the change is acceptable to the end-users who will be affected.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ownership:&lt;/strong&gt; Clearly defined responsibilities for the change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Managers/Stakeholders:&lt;/strong&gt; Individuals who will be impacted by the change or have a vested interest in its outcome.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Impact Analysis:&lt;/strong&gt; Assessing the potential effects of a change across the organization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Risk Value:&lt;/strong&gt; Quantifying the risk associated with the change.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lihon on Far Reaching:&lt;/strong&gt; (Likely a typo, possibly &amp;quot;Likelihood of far-reaching impact&amp;quot;) Assessing how widely the change might affect systems or users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sandbox Testing:&lt;/strong&gt; Testing the change in an isolated, non-production environment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Backout Plan:&lt;/strong&gt; A detailed plan for reversing a change if it fails or causes issues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Standard Operating Procedure (SOP):&lt;/strong&gt; Detailed, written instructions to achieve uniformity of the performance of a specific function.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.3.1 Technical Change Management&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This focuses on the technical aspects of managing changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow/Deny List:&lt;/strong&gt; Managing access based on explicit permissions or restrictions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Downtime:&lt;/strong&gt; Minimizing service interruptions during changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Legacy Applications:&lt;/strong&gt; Special considerations for older systems that may be fragile or difficult to modify.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Documentation:&lt;/strong&gt; Thoroughly documenting all changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Change Management Protocol:&lt;/strong&gt; The established set of rules and procedures for managing changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.4 Public Key Infrastructure (PKI)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;PKI is a framework that enables the secure exchange of information using public key cryptography. It involves:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Policies, Procedures, Hardware, Software, People:&lt;/strong&gt; A comprehensive system encompassing all these elements.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Digital Certificates:&lt;/strong&gt; Used to create, distribute, manage, store, and revoke digital certificates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Symmetric Encryption&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses a single, shared secret key for both encryption and decryption. It&#39;s fast but key distribution can be a challenge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Asymmetric Encryption (Public Key Cryptography)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uses two mathematically related keys: a public key and a private key.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Data encrypted with the public key can only be decrypted with the corresponding private key, and vice-versa.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Relies on complex mathematical problems involving large prime numbers and randomization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Escrow:&lt;/strong&gt; A system where a copy of a private key is held by a third party, often for recovery purposes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.4.1 Encryption: Protecting Data at Rest and in Transit&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Encryption is the process of converting information or data into a code to prevent unauthorized access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disk Encryption:&lt;/strong&gt; Tools like BitLocker and VeraCrypt encrypt entire disk drives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Stretching/Key Strengthening:&lt;/strong&gt; Techniques that make a weak key stronger by increasing the computational cost of brute-force attacks, adding additional overhead for attackers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.4.2 Key Exchange&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The process by which cryptographic keys are securely exchanged between two parties.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.4.3 Encryption Technologies&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Various hardware and software solutions support encryption:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trusted Platform Module (TPM):&lt;/strong&gt; A secure cryptoprocessor that stores cryptographic keys and protects them from malicious software.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hardware Security Module (HSM):&lt;/strong&gt; A physical computing device that safeguards and manages digital keys for strong authentication and provides cryptoprocessing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;**&lt;strong&gt;Key Management System (KMS):&lt;/strong&gt; A system for managing cryptographic keys throughout their lifecycle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Secure Enclave:&lt;/strong&gt; A separate, isolated processor within a device (e.g., a smartphone) that has its own boot ROM and monitors the boot process. It provides real-time memory encryption and often includes a true random number generator for strong cryptographic operations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.4.4 Obfuscation: Hiding Information&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obfuscation techniques aim to make information difficult to understand or interpret, but it&#39;s not true security.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steganography:&lt;/strong&gt; Hiding information in plain sight, often by embedding it within another file, such as an image (the &amp;quot;covertext&amp;quot;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concealed Writing:&lt;/strong&gt; A general term for hidden messages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tokenization:&lt;/strong&gt; Replacing sensitive data with a non-sensitive placeholder (a &amp;quot;token&amp;quot;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Near-Field Communication (NFC):&lt;/strong&gt; A short-range wireless technology that can be used for data transfer, but also has security implications if not properly secured.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Masking:&lt;/strong&gt; Obscuring specific data elements within a dataset to protect sensitive information while maintaining its usability for testing or analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.4.5 Hashing &amp;amp; Digital Signatures: Integrity and Authenticity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hashing:&lt;/strong&gt; Creates a one-way function where data cannot be recovered from its hash. Good hash functions should not have collisions (different inputs producing the same output). MD5 is an example of a hash function that is now deprecated due to collision vulnerabilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Salted Hashes:&lt;/strong&gt; Adding a random string (salt) to a password before hashing it, making rainbow table attacks (precomputed hash tables) ineffective.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.4.6 Blockchain Technology: Distributed Trust&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distributed Ledger:&lt;/strong&gt; A decentralized database shared and synchronized across multiple sites, institutions, or geographies.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Everyone Has It:&lt;/strong&gt; Each participant in the network has a copy of the entire ledger, ensuring transparency and immutability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;1.4.7 Certificates: Root of Trust&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Root of Trust:&lt;/strong&gt; A highly trusted authority (often a Certificate Authority) that serves as the foundation for trust in a PKI.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Certificate Authorities (CAs):&lt;/strong&gt; Trusted third parties that issue and manage digital certificates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Revocation:&lt;/strong&gt; The process of invalidating a digital certificate before its expiration date.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Online Certificate Status Protocol (OCSP):&lt;/strong&gt; A protocol used to obtain the revocation status of a digital certificate in real-time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.1 Threat Actors: Who Are They and What Do They Want?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding threat actors involves identifying who they are, their motivations, and their capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Internal/External:&lt;/strong&gt; Threat actors can originate from within an organization (insiders) or from outside.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Motivation:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Exfiltration:&lt;/strong&gt; Stealing sensitive data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Espionage:&lt;/strong&gt; Gaining secret information, often for state or corporate advantage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Service Disruption:&lt;/strong&gt; Causing outages or hindering operations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Blackmail:&lt;/strong&gt; Extorting money or favors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Financial Gain:&lt;/strong&gt; Direct monetary profit (e.g., ransomware).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Beliefs/Ethical:&lt;/strong&gt; Driven by ideological or ethical convictions (e.g., hacktivists).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Revenge:&lt;/strong&gt; Seeking retribution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disruption and Chaos:&lt;/strong&gt; Causing general disorder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;War:&lt;/strong&gt; State-sponsored cyber warfare.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Types of Threat Actors:&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;External Entities:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;National States:&lt;/strong&gt; Nation-states engage in constant attacks with massive resources, often associated with Advanced Persistent Threats (APTs).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unskilled Attackers:&lt;/strong&gt; Individuals with limited technical knowledge, often using readily available tools. They can be both internal and external.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hacktivist:&lt;/strong&gt; Motivated by philosophical or political beliefs. They can also be internal. Their actions often include DoS attacks, website defacement, or releasing private documents. Funding may be limited.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Insider Entities:&lt;/strong&gt; Individuals within an organization. They have access to internal resources and often possess medium-level sophistication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Organized Crime:&lt;/strong&gt; Almost always external, driven by financial gain. They are highly sophisticated, often employing tactics like ransomware.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shadow IT:&lt;/strong&gt; Employees or departments working around official IT policies, building their own infrastructure, which can create security vulnerabilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Going Rogue:&lt;/strong&gt; An individual acting independently against organizational policies or norms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.2 Common Threat Vectors: How Attacks Happen&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Threat vectors are the paths or methods attackers use to gain unauthorized access to systems or networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Message-Based Vectors:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Phishing:&lt;/strong&gt; Deceptive emails or messages designed to trick recipients into revealing sensitive information or performing actions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SMS (Short Message Service):&lt;/strong&gt; Used for smishing attacks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;File-Based Vectors:&lt;/strong&gt; Malicious code embedded in files.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Voice Call Vectors:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vishing:&lt;/strong&gt; Phishing conducted over the phone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;War Dialing:&lt;/strong&gt; Automatically dialing phone numbers to find open modems or systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Call Tampering:&lt;/strong&gt; Intercepting or altering phone calls.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spam over IP:&lt;/strong&gt; Unsolicited messages sent over Voice over IP (VoIP) systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Removable Device Vectors:&lt;/strong&gt; Malware spread via USB drives or other portable media.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vulnerable Software Vectors:&lt;/strong&gt; Exploiting weaknesses in software.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Client-Based:&lt;/strong&gt; Exploiting vulnerabilities in client-side applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Agentless:&lt;/strong&gt; Attacks that don&#39;t require installing an agent on the target system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unsupported Systems Vectors:&lt;/strong&gt; Exploiting vulnerabilities in outdated or unpatched operating systems and applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unsecure Network Vectors:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open Service Ports:&lt;/strong&gt; Unnecessary open ports that can be exploited.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Firewall Rules:&lt;/strong&gt; Misconfigured or weak firewall rules.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Default Credentials:&lt;/strong&gt; Using default usernames and passwords that are easily guessed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Supply Chain Vectors:&lt;/strong&gt; Attacks targeting vulnerabilities in the supply chain, often through third-party vendors like Managed Service Providers (MSPs).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.2.1 Phishing: The Art of Deception&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Phishing is a common social engineering technique that uses tricks and misdirection to manipulate individuals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Email Phishing:&lt;/strong&gt; The most common form, using deceptive emails.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Typosquatting:&lt;/strong&gt; Registering domain names that are slight misspellings of legitimate ones to trick users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pretexting:&lt;/strong&gt; Creating a fabricated scenario (pretext) to gain trust and obtain information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Vishing:&lt;/strong&gt; Phishing conducted over voice calls (phone).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Smishing:&lt;/strong&gt; Phishing conducted via SMS messages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.2.2 Impersonation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pretext:&lt;/strong&gt; A fabricated scenario used to gain trust and obtain information, often a key component of impersonation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.2.3 Watering Hole Attack&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An attack where a cyberattacker compromises a website frequently visited by a target group, hoping to infect members of that group. Often countered by a layered defense strategy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.2.4 Other Social Engineering Techniques&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Misinformation/Disinformation:&lt;/strong&gt; Spreading false or misleading information to manipulate individuals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.3 Memory Injections: Exploiting System Memory&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Memory injection attacks involve injecting malicious code directly into a process&#39;s memory space.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Malware Runs in Memory:&lt;/strong&gt; Malware often operates directly in memory to evade detection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Memory Forensics:&lt;/strong&gt; Analyzing memory dumps to detect and investigate malicious activity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DLLs (Dynamic Link Libraries):&lt;/strong&gt; Malware can inject itself into legitimate DLLs or load malicious ones.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Threads:&lt;/strong&gt; Malware can create or hijack threads within a process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Buffers:&lt;/strong&gt; Memory buffers can be exploited.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Management Functions:&lt;/strong&gt; Malware can interfere with memory management functions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Malware Hiding:&lt;/strong&gt; Malware can either hide itself within an existing process or create a new, malicious process.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.3.1 Buffer Overflows&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overwriting Buffer of Memory:&lt;/strong&gt; Occurs when a program attempts to write more data into a fixed-size memory buffer than it can hold, overflowing into adjacent memory locations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bounds Checking:&lt;/strong&gt; A defense mechanism that checks if data being written to a buffer will exceed its allocated size.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Repeatable:&lt;/strong&gt; Buffer overflows are often repeatable, meaning they can be reliably exploited.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.3.2 Race Conditions&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When Two Events Happen at the Same Time:&lt;/strong&gt; Occur when the outcome of a process depends on the sequence or timing of other uncontrollable events.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time-of-Check to Time-of-Use (TOCTOU) Attack:&lt;/strong&gt; A type of race condition where a system&#39;s state changes between the time it is checked and the time it is used, leading to a vulnerability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.3.3 Malicious Update&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trusted Sources:&lt;/strong&gt; Attackers can compromise trusted update mechanisms to deliver malicious updates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Backups:&lt;/strong&gt; Regular backups are crucial for recovery from malicious updates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.3.4 Operating Systems Security&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regular Updates:&lt;/strong&gt; Operating systems should be updated regularly to patch vulnerabilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patch Tuesday:&lt;/strong&gt; Microsoft&#39;s monthly release of security updates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.3.5 SQL Injection&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bad Programming:&lt;/strong&gt; A common web vulnerability caused by insecure coding practices.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SQL Injection:&lt;/strong&gt; Occurs when an attacker inserts malicious SQL code into input fields, which is then executed by the database.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.3.6 Cross-Site Scripting (XSS)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Takes Advantage of Trust:&lt;/strong&gt; XSS attacks exploit the trust a user has in a legitimate website.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Complex:&lt;/strong&gt; XSS attacks can be complex and difficult to detect.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;JavaScript-Based:&lt;/strong&gt; Mostly relies on injecting malicious JavaScript code into web pages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Non-Persistent (Reflected) XSS:&lt;/strong&gt; The malicious script is reflected off the web server and executed in the user&#39;s browser. It&#39;s not stored on the server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Persistent (Stored) XSS:&lt;/strong&gt; The malicious script is permanently stored on the target servers (e.g., in a database) and delivered to users when they access the vulnerable page.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.3.7 Hardware Vulnerabilities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hardware can have vulnerabilities that are difficult to detect and patch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OS Access:&lt;/strong&gt; Some hardware may have an operating system but no direct user access, making them perfect entry points for attackers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IoT (Internet of Things):&lt;/strong&gt; IoT devices are often vulnerable due to weak security, default credentials, and lack of updates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Firmware:&lt;/strong&gt; Software embedded in hardware. Often, only the vendor can modify it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;End of Life (EOL)/End of Service Life (EOSL):&lt;/strong&gt; When hardware or software reaches its EOL/EOSL, it no longer receives security updates, making it vulnerable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Legacy Platforms:&lt;/strong&gt; Older systems that are no longer supported or updated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.3.8 Virtualization Security&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VM Escape Protection:&lt;/strong&gt; Measures to prevent a virtual machine (VM) from breaking out of its virtualized environment and accessing the host system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Resource Reuse:&lt;/strong&gt; Securely managing the reuse of virtualized resources to prevent data leakage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.3.9 Cloud-Specific Vulnerabilities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cloud environments introduce unique security challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authentication Bypass:&lt;/strong&gt; Bypassing authentication mechanisms to gain unauthorized access.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Directory Traversal:&lt;/strong&gt; Exploiting vulnerabilities to access files and directories outside of the intended web root.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remote Code Execution:&lt;/strong&gt; Executing arbitrary code on a remote server.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Out of Bounds Write:&lt;/strong&gt; Writing data beyond the allocated memory buffer, potentially leading to code execution.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.3.10 Supply Chain Vulnerabilities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Many Parts:&lt;/strong&gt; Modern systems rely on many components from various suppliers, each introducing potential vulnerabilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Service Providers:&lt;/strong&gt; Compromised service providers can introduce vulnerabilities into your systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hardware Providers:&lt;/strong&gt; Vulnerabilities in hardware components.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Software Providers:&lt;/strong&gt; Vulnerabilities in third-party software.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.3.11 Misconfiguration Vulnerabilities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open Permissions:&lt;/strong&gt; Files or directories with overly permissive access rights.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unsecured Admin Accounts:&lt;/strong&gt; Administrator accounts with weak passwords or no multi-factor authentication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Insecure Protocols:&lt;/strong&gt; Using outdated or unencrypted protocols (e.g., Telnet instead of SSH).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Default Settings:&lt;/strong&gt; Leaving default configurations unchanged, which are often insecure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open Ports and Services:&lt;/strong&gt; Unnecessary open ports or running services that can be exploited.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.3.12 Mobile Device Vulnerabilities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Jailbreaking/Rooting:&lt;/strong&gt; Modifying a mobile device&#39;s operating system to remove vendor restrictions, which can introduce security risks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sideloading:&lt;/strong&gt; Installing applications from sources other than official app stores, increasing the risk of malware.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.3.13 Zero-Day Vulnerabilities&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Not Found Yet:&lt;/strong&gt; A vulnerability that is unknown to the vendor and has no patch available. Attackers can exploit these before defenses are in place.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.4 Malware: Malicious Software&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Malware is a broad term for any software designed to cause damage, disrupt systems, or gain unauthorized access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ransomware:&lt;/strong&gt; Malware that encrypts a victim&#39;s files and demands a ransom payment for decryption.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.4.1 Viruses and Worms&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Virus:&lt;/strong&gt; Malicious code that attaches itself to legitimate programs and requires user interaction to spread. It can replicate and move between systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fileless Virus:&lt;/strong&gt; A type of malware that operates entirely in memory, leaving no traces on the hard drive.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Worm:&lt;/strong&gt; Self-replicating malware that doesn&#39;t need user interaction to spread. It uses network vulnerabilities to propagate rapidly, often bypassing firewalls.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.4.2 Spyware and Bloatware&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spyware:&lt;/strong&gt; Malware designed to secretly gather information about a user&#39;s activities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bloatware:&lt;/strong&gt; Unwanted software pre-installed on devices, often consuming resources and potentially posing security risks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.4.3 Other Malware Types&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keylogger:&lt;/strong&gt; Records keystrokes to capture sensitive information like passwords.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Logic Bomb:&lt;/strong&gt; Malicious code that lies dormant until a specific condition is met (e.g., a date, a user action).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rootkit:&lt;/strong&gt; A stealthy type of malware designed to hide its presence and other malicious processes on a system, often by modifying core operating system components.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.4.4 Physical Attacks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brute-Force:&lt;/strong&gt; Repeatedly trying different combinations to guess passwords or unlock systems.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RFID Cloning:&lt;/strong&gt; Copying the data from RFID (Radio-Frequency Identification) cards to create duplicates.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Environmental Attacks:&lt;/strong&gt; Attacks that exploit environmental factors.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Turning Off Power:&lt;/strong&gt; Causing a power outage to disrupt services.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HVAC (Heating, Ventilation, and Air Conditioning):&lt;/strong&gt; Manipulating HVAC systems to damage equipment or disrupt operations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fire Suppression:&lt;/strong&gt; Disabling fire suppression systems to cause damage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.4.5 Denial of Service (DoS)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Force Service to Fail:&lt;/strong&gt; An attack designed to make a machine or network resource unavailable to its intended users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sometimes Friendly:&lt;/strong&gt; Can sometimes be unintentional (e.g., a legitimate surge in traffic).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Distributed Denial of Service (DDoS):&lt;/strong&gt; A DoS attack launched from multiple compromised computer systems (a &amp;quot;botnet&amp;quot;) to overwhelm a target. Can be reflected and amplified using vulnerable servers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.4.6 DNS Attacks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DNS Spoofing/Poisoning:&lt;/strong&gt; Injecting false DNS (Domain Name System) records into a DNS resolver&#39;s cache, redirecting users to malicious websites.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Domain Hijacking:&lt;/strong&gt; Gaining unauthorized control over a domain name.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;URL Hijacking:&lt;/strong&gt; Redirecting users from a legitimate URL to a malicious one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Typosquatting/Brandjacking:&lt;/strong&gt; Registering domain names that are common misspellings or variations of legitimate brands to trick users.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.4.7 Wireless Attacks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wireless Deauthentication:&lt;/strong&gt; Sending deauthentication frames to disconnect clients from a Wi-Fi network (802.11 standard).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;802.11ac:&lt;/strong&gt; A Wi-Fi standard.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;RF (Radio Frequency) Jamming:&lt;/strong&gt; Deliberately interfering with radio signals to disrupt wireless communication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wireless Jamming:&lt;/strong&gt; A general term for disrupting wireless signals, often by broadcasting random data.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fox Hunting:&lt;/strong&gt; The process of locating a hidden radio transmitter, often used in wireless security to find rogue access points.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.4.8 On-Path Attack (Man-in-the-Middle)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ARP Spoofing/Poisoning:&lt;/strong&gt; Manipulating ARP (Address Resolution Protocol) tables to redirect network traffic through an attacker&#39;s machine.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On-Path Browser/Man-in-the-Browser Attack:&lt;/strong&gt; Malware that intercepts and modifies web traffic within the user&#39;s web browser.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.4.9 Replay Attacks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Need Raw Network Data:&lt;/strong&gt; Involve capturing legitimate data transmission and retransmitting it to impersonate a legitimate user or system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Pass the Hash:&lt;/strong&gt; An attack where an attacker steals a password hash and uses it to authenticate to a system without cracking the hash.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Session Hijacking (Sidejacking):&lt;/strong&gt; Stealing a user&#39;s session ID to take over their active session.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;E2E (End-to-End) Encryption:&lt;/strong&gt; Crucial for preventing replay attacks by encrypting data from the source to the destination.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.4.10 Malicious Code&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;General term for any code designed to perform unauthorized or harmful actions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.4.11 Application Attacks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Injection:&lt;/strong&gt; Inserting malicious code into an application (e.g., SQL injection, command injection).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Replay:&lt;/strong&gt; Replaying captured data to gain unauthorized access.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Privilege Escalation:&lt;/strong&gt; Gaining higher-level permissions than initially authorized.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cross-Site Request Forgery (CSRF):&lt;/strong&gt; Tricking a web browser into executing an unwanted action on a trusted site where the user is authenticated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Client-Server Codes:&lt;/strong&gt; Exploiting vulnerabilities in the interaction between client and server applications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Directory Traversal:&lt;/strong&gt; Accessing files and directories outside of the intended web root.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.4.12 Cryptographic Attacks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hash Collision:&lt;/strong&gt; Finding two different inputs that produce the same hash output.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Birthday Attack:&lt;/strong&gt; A type of cryptographic attack that exploits the mathematics behind the birthday problem to find hash collisions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Downgrade Attack:&lt;/strong&gt; Forcing a system to use a weaker, less secure version of a protocol or algorithm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SSL Stripping:&lt;/strong&gt; An attack that downgrades an HTTPS connection to HTTP, allowing the attacker to intercept traffic.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.4.13 Password Attacks&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Should Be Hashed:&lt;/strong&gt; Passwords should always be stored as hashes, not in plain text.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Spraying Attack:&lt;/strong&gt; Attempting a single password against many accounts to avoid account lockouts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brute-Force:&lt;/strong&gt; Systematically trying every possible combination of characters until the correct password is found.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;2.4.14 Indicators of Compromise (IoC)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Any Event that Indicates an Intrusion:&lt;/strong&gt; Evidence that a system or network has been compromised.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Account Lockout:&lt;/strong&gt; Repeated failed login attempts leading to an account being locked.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Concurrent Session Usage:&lt;/strong&gt; A single user account being logged in from multiple locations simultaneously.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This overview provides a foundational understanding of key cybersecurity concepts essential for the CompTIA Security+ exam and for anyone entering the field. From implementing robust controls and understanding the CIA Triad to identifying various threat actors and their attack vectors, a comprehensive approach to security is paramount in today&#39;s digital landscape. Continuous learning and vigilance are key to staying ahead of evolving threats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Mert Biricik</name>
    </author>
  </entry>
</feed>